<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts | Pratham</title><link>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/</link><atom:link href="https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Posts</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 03:29:39 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/media/icon_hu5f33b233649b5e31fe08b3066c6ae9cb_405_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Posts</title><link>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/</link></image><item><title>Looking back on 2023</title><link>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/reflecting2024/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 03:29:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/reflecting2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s currently 4:10 AM on December 24, 2023, and I am sitting in the glow of the computer screen, reflecting on what a rollercoaster this year has been. I haven&amp;rsquo;t really been frequent on blogging; maybe 2024 will change things.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I entered the 4th semester in January, little did I know it would be one of the best semesters of my undergrad. I had just landed a summer internship at &lt;a href="https://yonseivnl.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Yonsei Vision and Learning Labs, Seoul&lt;/a>, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t have asked for more. Diving into core Computer Science courses for the first time was exhilarating, to say the least.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Come March, after navigating through weeks of uncertainty and enduring over seven hours of continuous and intense interviews, I was appointed as the Coordinator of the &lt;a href="https://www.pclub.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Programming Club&lt;/a> at IIT Kanpur for the 2023-2024 tenure. It felt like everything was falling into place.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In May, I left for Korea for 2.5 months. I performed research under one of the best professors I&amp;rsquo;ve ever met, Prof. Jonghyun Choi. However, the fever of the intern season meant that my days were spent in the lab, and evenings, often stretching till 2-3 AM, in a coffee shop, rigorously preparing for the upcoming intern season. I spent my weekends sightseeing, and in my 10 weeks, I would have covered most of the tourist spots of Seoul. Korea is a beautiful country, and I would definitely love to visit again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img src="featured.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fifth semester started in August with one of the lowest points in my life. The intern season had started, and I had been very stingy in my intern applications, applying only to a handful of companies on day 1. I faced surprising rejections from all of them while all my friends got offers. This blow to my self-esteem led me to take a brief retreat back home. Fortunately, I landed a decent placement with Adobe Research in the second week.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The semester was also hectic, with most nights spent on assignments. My friends and I also managed to pull off a Goa trip (cliché!), which made the semester sweeter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was in this semester, I got introduced to High Performance Computing when we received an email that Professors Preeti and Swarnendu were forming a team for &lt;a href="https://www.studentclustercompetition.us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ISCSCC24&lt;/a>. Having no experience at all in this domain, I decided to give it a shot along with one of my friends, Aditya Bangar. We managed to get selected (and I was nominated as the captain) for the IITK team, and our team also got selected to take part in the final event. The work at the Programming Club was also picking up pace, and I decided that the long-running dating app of IIT Kanpur, Puppy Love, built by Saksham Sharma, needed a revamp. I envisioned this with one of my friends, Nikhil, and we got into the development phase of PuppyLove2.0 (blog on it coming soon). I decided to skip participating in the Inter IIT Tech Meet this year as well because I was already loaded up with so much stuff.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>December was a month of new endeavors. I attended a workshop on CUDA programming, and, spurred by a newfound interest in Systems, I embarked on a project to build my own OS using Rust. Our team also made significant progress on PuppyLove2.0, now in its deployment phase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Looking back, this year had its share of regrets, but undeniably, it ranks as one of the best in my life.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr></description></item><item><title>How to Land a CSE Research Internship Abroad - My Views</title><link>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/research_intern/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 19:10:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://prathamsahu52.github.io/post/research_intern/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Note: I had done a Research Intern in my second year at &lt;a href="https://yonseivnl.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Yonsei Vision and Learning Laboratories&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="route-1-via-programs">Route 1: Via Programs&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Some internship programs take in interns during their second-year summers. Information about these programs can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/himahuja/Research-Internships-for-Undergraduates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.
In IIT Kanpur, the OIR(Office of International Relations) also arranges for internships with a few labs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="route-2-via-cold-mailing">Route 2: Via Cold Mailing&lt;/h1>
&lt;h3 id="step-1-decide-your-research-topic">Step 1: Decide Your Research Topic&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Selecting your research topic is a crucial initial step. Be certain of your choice as switching topics later can lead to a significant loss of valuable time. In Computer Science, research topics generally categorize into the following areas:(Taken from &lt;a href="https://csrankings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CSRankings&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Computer Vision&lt;/li>
&lt;li>NLP&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Traditional Mathematical Machine Learning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Web and IR&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Systems:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Architecture and Organisation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Systems&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Security&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Databases&lt;/li>
&lt;li>HPC&lt;/li>
&lt;li>OS&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Programming Languages&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Software Engineering&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Theory:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Algorithms&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Logic&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cryptography&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Miscellaneous:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Computer Graphics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Parallel Computing and Visualization&lt;/li>
&lt;li>HCI&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Robotics&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="step-2-databasing">Step 2: Databasing&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Begin by identifying Professors and Labs that focus on your area of interest. Be proactive as some programs announce openings throughout the year.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Start with &lt;a href="https://csrankings.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CSRankings&lt;/a>, which is a comprehensive repository of universities and faculty members.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Don&amp;rsquo;t rely solely on rankings to judge the quality of a lab; instead, delve into the research topics that intrigue you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conduct thorough research and compile a list of Labs and Professors you find appealing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remember that not all faculty members may be listed on CSRankings, so you should also visit the computer science department websites directly, such as the one for &lt;a href="http://www.iitk.ac.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IIT Kanpur&lt;/a>, to discover more researchers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Focus on Professors who are Principal Investigators (PIs) of labs as they typically have the funds to support interns.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="some-popular-labsgroups-to-consider">Some Popular Labs/Groups to Consider:&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.inria.fr/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Inria&lt;/a> - The French National Institute for computer science and applied mathematics.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cispa.saarland/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CISPA&lt;/a> - Helmholtz Center for Information Security.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>For those interested in Computer Vision, check out this list of &lt;a href="https://medium.com/maheshkkumar/computer-vision-research-laboratories-fa344a129b3e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Computer Vision Research Laboratories&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Suggestions for additional resources are welcome!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-3-approaching-the-lab-via-email">Step 3: Approaching the Lab via Email&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Email communication is a critical step in the application process and greatly influences whether your email is engaged with or disregarded.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dos">Do’s:&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Be Concise:&lt;/strong> Get straight to the point without unnecessary details.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Specify Context:&lt;/strong> In the opening paragraph, clearly state the purpose of your email, when you&amp;rsquo;d like to intern, and your area of research interest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Express Interest:&lt;/strong> Explain why you are drawn to research and to the lab in particular.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Personalize:&lt;/strong> Tailor each email to the respective professor by mentioning specific details from their recent publications, showing genuine interest in their work.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Attachments:&lt;/strong> Include links to your resume and transcripts, preferably hosted on a reliable platform like Google Drive.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Note: For privacy reasons, the content of my personal emails is not included here. Please contact me directly if you would like to use my email as a template.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-4-handling-replies">Step 4: Handling Replies&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Receiving a reply, positive or negative, is part of the process.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No Response:&lt;/strong> If there is silence, consider revising your email approach.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rejections:&lt;/strong> Don&amp;rsquo;t be disheartened by a &amp;rsquo;no&amp;rsquo;. Often, the reasons are explained and it&amp;rsquo;s not always about your qualifications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Interviews:&lt;/strong> If an interview is arranged, clarify your intentions for wanting to join the lab. Revisit the papers you referenced in your email to prepare. Confidence and clear communication are key as professors and researchers are typically empathetic.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fun Fact:&lt;/strong> While I was at Imagica (a theme park) enjoying a trip with my friends, I received an email notifying me that my interview for YVnL was unexpectedly scheduled for that very evening. I left the park and found a hotel nearby to conduct the interview. Surprisingly, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared at all, but I believe that sometimes being underprepared can actually be beneficial—it forces you to be authentic and think on your feet!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong> This guide is tailored for students seeking research internships in computer science and engineering (CSE) abroad.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>